[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host joavan asoni and
today we'll be discussing identity
orchestration with Eric Holden Eric
founded and scaled secur CLE trust and
simplified simplified was the first
identity as a service company he served
as a senior vice president and general
manager at Oracle where he ran the
identity and security business worldwide
and he was also the co coauthor of Sul
the Sul standard created the first pre
integrated single sonon platform and
identity fabric Eric welcome to software
engineering radio is there anything I
miss that you'd like to add no that was
a great introduction Giovani thanks for
having me let's start with ref pressure
about identity management so today we'll
be talking about identity orchestration
which is about identity management so I
think is a good idea to start with a
refresher about what identity
orchestration is and maybe give also an
example a practical example so how
listeners will have a good mental model
in their heads yeah happy to so when you
think about identity management first
and it's a simple concept of how do you
manage what users can access and what
they can do inside of an
application and that is the gist of
identity management now when you go
further into the details there's a good
model I think of of the six A's so the
first one is authentication so how do
you manage how you know a user is who
they represent themselves are they using
passwords or tokens the second one is
access control and this determines
whether a user can get to an application
or to data that they're trying to and
third one is authorization and most
often this is for instance within an
application can a user do a transaction
can they do a transaction for a certain
amount of money or something like that
the fourth one is the attributes and the
attributes about a user that are used in
these policy decisions is sensitive so
you need to make sure that those
attributes are secure the fifth one
is Administration or governance and how
you manage those user accounts who has a
membership in various groups and so
forth and then the last one or the sixth
one is audit and so you need to be able
to see a log of what users did over time
and so taken together these six A's
represent identity management so now the
question of what is identity
orchestration and identity orchestration
is a new way to think about identity if
you have multiple clouds if you have
multiple environments and you're running
in a distributed world and so what we do
with orchestration is similar to what
the infrastructure world has done for
some time for instance like using
terraform to automate and go do things
in a particular sequence or kubernetes
which is another way to orchestrate your
compute so what we did with identity
orchestration was say well why don't we
apply some of those same concepts of
abstraction and automation to the
identity so we can make these
distributed multivendor multicloud
worlds work in a more seamless way so
some people talk about identity
orchestration as kubernetes or terraform
for identity so that might be a good way
to think about what identity
orchestration can do so here we we are
talking about situation where we have
different identity management systems
and identity orchestration is a way of
actually making all these disparate
identity management system as if they
were one somehow that's exactly right
and that we do through abstraction so
absolutely normalize the different apis
that the identity systems the idps or
the identity providers that they expose
created a layer that integrates across
all of those so that when you build a
new application it doesn't have to be
tightly coupled to any one of those
identity systems instead it talks to the
abstraction layer and through the
decoupling of the application from the
identity provider it allows you to
switch out different providers without
changing the application so you can go
from an old to a new identity system
behind the abstraction layer and not
have to refactor or do anything to your
application okay from a business point
of view what are the key challenges that
identity orchestration helps to address
so from let's say non-technical
perspective more of a business
perspective yeah I think one of the most
common two use cases for
orchestration is
modernization so taking your
applications and moving them to the
cloud and in that world you need to
switch the legacy on premise identity
system with a cloud-based one so
modernization is a big important use
case because in the absence of an
abstraction layer you're going to have
to rewrite your application and that's
very expensive takes a lot of time the
second maybe business scenario is with
mergers and Acquisitions so when you
think about one company acquiring
another one very often you'll find one
company has different technology stacked
than than the other and so you need to
have a way to have these two worlds
coexist for instance you may have one
company that's a Microsoft shop they use
everything from Azure including the
entra identity provider and then they
acquire a company that has been using
OCTA for years and so now you have a
situation where you need to make
Microsoft and OCTA coexist as you
probably know those companies are very
competitive and they don't like to play
well with the other their answer is oh
throw them out and put everything on us
but that's not practical for a lot of
reasons right so from a business
standpoint the ability to be able to
merge the applications and the different
identity system allows you to handle
these coexistence use cases a lot more
seamlessly and then the last use case I
would suggest is when people are trying
to get rid of passwords and like Legacy
applications often rely on password
authentication that's problematic
because of fishing and breaches that
come out of that weak credential so a
lot of great Solutions on the market
like pass keys and multiactor
authentication and tokens and all these
really effective ways to eliminate the
use of passwords but the problem is
you've got this new technology and you
need to make it work on your old
applications in so in that case you can
use an abstraction layer to link up
modern authentication with a legacy
application and so that allows you to
increase the security very quickly and
meet compliance from a business
standpoint and eliminate the exposure to
credential compromise that passwords
have so whether it's mergers and
Acquisitions
modernization or getting rid of
passwords orchestration has been a very
Universal kind of tool okay so basically
if when we talk about merges and
Acquisitions is the situation where
maybe you have employees that need to
access systems of what was the other
company before but you don't want to
give them a different set of
credentials yeah absolutely and it's as
practical and simple as if in the merger
and acquisition case you have the new
company and the old company they have
two different email addresses right
before the merger they were different
companies so you may have someone like
myself I could have an account at Eric
at oldco but I want to access the new
applications and I don't have the Eric
at newco email address and so what the
orchestration layer can do is say well I
know you're Eric at oldco and I'm going
to map that to a different identity user
ID in the cloud identity system so that
when that user logs in they get to the
applications but they use the old email
instead of the new one and it goes the
other direction so the new company has
their emails will then work as an
identifier for the Legacy applications
so names space mapping is a very common
very hardto do problem if you don't have
an abstraction layer that you can use to
do that mapping and so that is really
powerful use case for ation okay that's
clear and what are the main differences
between systems that are on cloud and on
premises I mean are there any key
differences when we talk about them in
the context of identity management and
orchestration I would say in 2023
there's a lot of good options for
different capabilities in the cloud
there's fewer options for systems that
are running on premises because all the
vendors have focused on
going to the cloud so you'll see more
capabilities in your Cloud identity
systems than you will on premises in the
Legacy some of the the key things that I
think people get when you go to the
cloud is someone else manages all of
this infrastructure and identity is one
of the most Mission critical parts of
any infrastructure if your security and
identity goes down your applications are
offline line so you think about all of
the redundancy and the resilience that
you need to think about I think the
cloudbased identity systems have done a
great job and they have a really strong
position in resiliency but it's not
always there so another way to think
about how to Leverage The Best of both
of those worlds is you could use
orchestration to primarily use the cloud
identity system but if there was a
outage on the net network if a storm
comes through and breaks the network
connection to the outside Cloud then
orchestration can fail that application
over to an on premises identity provider
and go into more of a backup mode until
your network services are reestablished
because you want to keep your
applications up and running so a lot of
capability in the cloud but now you got
a dependency on that the cloud is
available in the network and so I think
the way to mitigate those risks is to be
thinking about continuity both at the
application data and the identity layer
okay have you worked on any of these
systems with mix on the cloud and on
premises where you had to solve these
kind of problems yeah we do it actually
all the time some interesting use cases
too I think the most interesting one I
found was in Naval situations so cruise
ships which was a news to me are
floating data centers and they go out
and all of the kind of entertainment
that you sign up for and you want to
watch a show or you want to get a
reservation for dinner and all of that
that's all done now on your phone and
the identity system of all of these
thousands of passengers who come on for
a cruise and they get off you have a lot
of churn thousands of users that come in
and leave every maybe a week or so and
the challenge is that when you're at C
you don't have access to the cloud in a
reliable way right they're nowhere near
a fiber optic connection because
naturally you know they have to use
satellites and things of that type so
that was a really interesting use case
because they said well look when we have
the ship in Port we can get all this
really fat pipe data that we can
synchronize things and do all of that
and as soon as we push off we go to like
99% smaller bandwidth and so that was a
really interesting use case when I was
at Oracle we did a lot of work with the
military and submarines have that same
problem because when they're underwater
they by definition they don't have
communication anywhere and so thinking
about identity that works in both modes
connected and disconnected it's kind of
interesting in this new distributed
multicloud world must be also quite
challenging very challenging as far as I
know so sometimes these systems have
also so Ware that is not necessarily the
most modern stuff you know it's like if
you see
entertainment things in the airplanes
they look like iPads but from the 1950s
maybe 60 you're right so that might add
an additional challenge to actually
manage ID entity properly I would
imagine it is you're right and I think
people get accustomed to how fast
technology changes in the consumer world
right your phone updating apps constant
ly and the websites they're always
updated but that's not the case in the
Enterprise you go to the Enterprise
these are applications I've seen some
that have been there for 20 years and
people don't know who built it well
they're left the company a long time ago
so they don't want to touch it they
don't want to have anything go wrong so
they say look just don't touch that
application but we need to move it to
the cloud how are we going to do that
and so find some really interesting it's
kind of like to imagine going to you
want to watch a stream streaming thing
on Netflix but then the only adapter on
the back of the television is the RCA
jacks and those I'm dating myself here
gavan but you know what how it used to
be you know plug it in the red the White
and the yellow and you know I'm of the
same generation and
exactly like ah I just wanted to work
and actually that's a good metaphor for
orchestration right you think about a
travel adapter and the way that you're
in the you're in Europe right now I'm in
the United States and if I were to bring
my laptop to London I would have to have
the British power adapter which by the
way is just not very efficient at all my
personal opinion but I guess that's the
American bias here but so what do I do I
don't want to buy a new laptop that I
bring to Europe that wouldn't make any
sense so instead I find an abstraction
layer of travel adapter and that becomes
the thing that I plug in the American
plug into one side and then I have
various adapters on the other and I
stick it into the appropriate unit in
wherever I'm going and that's in essence
what identity orchestration is able to
do you can plug the new stuff into the
old stuff without changing it because
all of that mapping is done at the
adapter or the abstraction layer yeah
yeah it seems to be a good analogy which
actually brings me to a question that I
had in mind that is are there any
characteristics of the identity
management systems that need to be
orchestrated that make them more
amenable to orchestration yeah I think
if I were looking for an identity
provider that is going to serve me the
best the one thing I would look for
giovan more than anything is standards
support because it is the lack of
Standards based integration that's
caused so much of the headache and so
the standards most of them all are
supported nowadays but the things that
I'd be looking for are does this provide
uh saml capability to do Federated
single sign on does this identity
provider use open ID connect does this
identity provider support pass Keys Pho
to if the answer is yes then that's a
lot easier to deploy and to switch
because everything's based on standards
it's really I think when people are
dealing with old and new that's where a
lot of the challenge is because when we
were building these applications 10
years ago I mean saml has been around
for 20 plus years now but in the very
beginning it existed but it wasn't
widely deployed and so it meant that
people were using what they had and that
means cookies and proprietary
authentication systems and sessions and
the only way you could pass data from
the IDP into the app would be through
HTTP headers so you have to think about
how do you bridge that old world with
the new and when you do it in modern
time You' be able to use like saml is
really well defined standard and it
handles all of the attributes and claims
in a very secure way so open ID connect
very similar derivative in a sense works
really well as at the same token the
last you mentioned apis and I think of
the other key thing not the first but
maybe the second or the third would be
the API availability and modern ones
today support restful interfaces more
than the old days there was a lot of
soap and that just was a lot more
overhead to do a very simple thing you
had to do a lot of complex stuff so look
for restful interfaces is that are also
standards based so what I mean in that
example would be there's a standard for
managing identity data called skim I
think is a simple Cloud identity
management is the acronym and that works
with rest and so I think look for a
standard look for a modern
implementation and You' be in really
good shape if you don't maybe you
inherited something that was predated
that availability then use orchestration
and that'll get you to where you need to
be it'll basically bring standards to
the Legacy stuff and I think that's
really helpful and how does this work in
the case of systems actually also not so
old systems also some being created now
where people actually create their own
identity management specific for the
system you know they create a login
password the roles and everything which
usually lives in the same database as
the rest of the data so if you have
systems like this to bring them under an
identity orchestration umbrella what do
we need to do is there some development
work necessary there yeah so very often
people have to build their own and it
usually starts like oh it's no big deal
we're building a trading application and
someone has to handle the user table and
so they say okay let's just put a table
in there and put our users in there and
I let's give them passwords because we
want to focus on the trading application
that's really interesting so they wind
up building rolling their own and it
generally doesn't have all of the
capabilities that you would get from a
third party so I think one thing to do
would be stop doing that because you're
not really saving all that much and
you're building a lot of technical debt
that gets really expensive to replace
and so I think off zero has done a lot
for developers who just want to solve
that login problem but don't want to
spend much time doing it you can get all
the great capabilities from these
identity as a service companies azero is
a good one there are others as well that
are Developer focused some new startups
that are coming out but let's say that
the ship is already sailed and we've got
to work with that embedded user table
then what I think one of the most
important things would be to get rid of
the dependence on the password and the
reason that is so important is that
close to 90% of security breaches that
lead to whether it's ransomware or other
kind of privacy laws come from a fishing
attack that compromised the password and
there's a whole host of reasons why that
is so weak in terms of protection but
suffice to say that we want to replace
that where we can with something that is
more robust like a multiactor
Authentication
like the QR codes or the authenticator
apps so when you've got that situation
what you can do is use the abstraction
layer to basically deploy software so
that the multiactor authentication is
what the user experiences they go
through they're redirected to a
authentication process that says
something like check the authenticator
app on your phone or look at this QR
code or use your pass key that that's
built into your your laptop right so
there's any number of ways that you do
that so that is the secure thing now we
need to link that trusted session with
this Legacy user table right and so at
that point what we want to do is look at
that user ID in that user table and we
can ignore the password for a moment so
you look at the user ID and you map that
to the user ID that is used for the
multiactor Authentication
and at that point you can pass that
session from the authentication flow
into the application using the user ID
as the common link between the two and
so uh you can ignore the password
because of the way that you deploy the
orchestration software is in the same
memory space as the application so
there's no way for someone to get in
there and to put in a fake
authentication saying oh I really did
pass authentication there's no way to do
that because of encryption and trust and
a lot of kind of the Gory details that
you don't have to worry about if you're
using the orchestration layer because
all of that is built into it okay and so
the facad handles all of that this also
means that there may be the need of some
development effort of some sorts to be
able to link the orchestration with this
old adoc mechanism generally not when
you use orchestration software right
because that software has the ability to
do the mapping and the account linking
and so it is kind of built into that
layer now if you didn't have
orchestration software and you wanted to
do that on your own absolutely having
orchestration software in this case okay
yeah using software helps you avoid
custom code okay and now something
slightly different so how does identity
orchestration affect the user experience
well in the best of cases the end user
doesn't know that this is happening at
all it's the same experience before and
after the deployment because it the
orchestration software is transparent
you drop it in front of your application
it works as a proxy or as a identity
service provider kind of interface so
the end user they go to the same place
that they log in and let's say
originally they use a password they go
to a portal login all of that is
unchanged what's happening under the
covers or behind the scenes is that the
orchestration software is saying okay
I'm not going to go to the old system
I'm going to go to the new system to
authenticate this user and to get
attributes and check permissions and all
of that so transparent to the end user
and on the other hand if you are
changing the authentication experience
because you want to bring in something
like passwordless authentic indication
now you need to roll that experience out
in a very thoughtful way because if a
user who's used to logging in seeing a
username and password all of a sudden
has a different experience we've been
training our users about hey if the
login page changes you're getting fished
and don't put your information in there
and so you get into the situation where
you want to be mindful on how to roll
that out and so I think there's a couple
of ways that you want to communicate a
change like strong authentication or
two- Factor authentication is coming to
our application tell people it's coming
so they know when they log in that at
some point they'll be given that option
and then you want to give them the
ability to do both use your user ID and
password or you can use your password
list token and over time they start to
see those two and then they go well
maybe they need to I don't know just
take a chance and try this new
two-factor thing and now all of a sudden
they can start to use that one moving
forward so I think it's just getting
around that conditioning of how you
treat the end user with employees it's
easier because you can force it with
customers it's a little bit more you
want to incent them so say for instance
tired of forgetting your password now
just use your phone and it's more secure
and more convenient so you can incent
people to try the more secure mechanism
but it is something you want to be very
mindful because you can get people
especially customers to say ah I'm
confused I'm not going to log in to this
Bank application because I don't want to
lose my money and I understand that but
if you educate people I think there's a
lot you can do to get them used to it
okay and what about the case where you
are integrating say a system there are
you know already multiactor
authentications but you have more than
one you have two three four because of I
don't know a merger and acquisition or
something and then you end up with a
systems that pretty much do the same
thing but maybe slightly different ways
yeah that's a very common problem gavani
and it happens because human nature I'll
give it a great example if we are all
passwordless at my company we don't have
any passwords of our applications use
two Factor
authentication and so for instance and I
fly a lot so if I'm on a plane and I
need to access something I need to have
a fallback authentication mechanism in
the event that I can't use a network
based one right and so I don't have my
keys right here but I have a pho token
on my keychain normally I like to use
the authenticator app that will go talk
to the cloud and say hey here's a code
that changes over time and that's really
easy especially if I have my phone which
is generally all the time but then I'm
on an airplane I can't get to the
network so it would be it really useful
if we can fall back to another
multiactor authentication mechanism like
my token that I plug into my laptop so
having because what you don't want to do
is say oh I can't find my
strong authentication system so use my
password because then that would just
bring your who's going to say oh
I of the authentication system the yeah
so you can't do that it's like locking
your convertible but having the top down
doesn't make any sense right but
orchestration in that situation can be
the capability of the or use this
mechanism or this other one where both
of these are strong authentication
mechanisms one could be an app the other
one could be a hardware token but that
is really important because people
forget things people go on airplanes and
so when you're thinking about how do we
make sure that we have multiple ways
that are still secure for a user to
authenticate that's where orchestration
can really help you in addition to the
merger and acquisition use case that you
talked about so you end up with a
situation where instead of having a
situation say oh down we have redundancy
is a mess you end up say h luckily we
have redundancy so we actually have a
way of avoiding disaster in case things
happen that's exactly right so you can
actually exploit that as an advantage
yes yes you're right multiple is helpful
in in some
cases are there any differences in how
orchestration works in the case of
services instead of humans you know when
we have any kind of services connected
to the network that need a level of
authentication authorization because of
the way they're done is there any any
impact yes there is I think when you're
talking about a service account or API
and someone was joking saying apis are
people too I don't know if I say that
but they have entities behind that right
it's a user who's accessing an
application that makes a transaction on
that user's behalf so what you have in
that situation is a need for continuity
of the user IDE identity from the
browser through to the back end hitting
an API that could be wherever and making
sure that you can't do something at the
API level that you couldn't do at the
browser level for instance and so being
able to have a way to basically move
from the browser have that session that
then can be handed to the API layer
that's a capability that the
orchestration layer can do so that way
you keep the consistency of the entity
even as it moves from a browser to an
API call another common thing is well
what about just the API that's doing
server to server request and at that
point you put the orchestration layer
acts as a proxy and enforces the
authentication and authorization at the
API layer and so even without having a
browser involved you can still will have
the orchestration layer intercept
basically the API calls and apply logic
like
authentication when you're dealing with
server to server hopefully you're not
using passwords because that's really
bad security but certificates are a lot
more common when you're dealing with
backend entities systems of system and
so at that point instead of using
enduser authentication you're going to
be relying on ceric certificates
typically you could have some API keys
but that's just another word for a
password and so I recommend people avoid
that anywhere whether you call it a
password or an API key and instead use
certificates and that still applies in
this world what would you do if you find
a situation where you have really
username and password for a service
account because I've seen systems in the
past where basically service to service
but still you needed to create basically
a user for a service is kind of you know
service is a person to kind of thing
seems to be MH so username and password
so I would expect some of those systems
to be still out there maybe not the the
most modern ones but as we know systens
tend to live long lives if they're
useful so in those situations how does
orchestration affect in service to
service interaction so I think in those
cases if I came into an environment they
had a lot of Legacy poorly architected
because they're using passwords one of
the first first things I would do is to
replace the on file system for the
password with something like a vault and
a key Vault Secrets manager that's less
about orchestration it's just more about
how you store secure secrets and
Technologies all the cloud platforms
have them you know Key Management
systems on Azure Hashi Corp makes a
really strong offering there so I guess
the reason I would start there is that
you could
without changing a lot of the relying
application handle those sensitive data
in a more secure way so that would be
the triage approach would be to hey
let's get this to be better than
vulnerable as putting it on the file
system or in some database or some user
table when you talk about orchestration
I think that also is a place where
orchestration software can talk with
those Secrets managers and get those
credentials for the service to service
authentication and so that's the second
step right put the vault in plays
Secrets manager and then you get the
orchestration to use that as well and
then you can extrapolate and go take
those credentials and use them further a
field but you got to get rid of the
vulnerability as much as you can where
it's most susceptible in the file system
and now something different about
identity life cycle management so when
we put an identity orchestration system
in place how do we manage the life cycle
of the identity you know adding like
onboarding offboarding employees so I
think the way the use case you're
bringing up illustrates the dichotomy in
identity which is on one hand you have
runtime systems so when someone is
logging in how do you authenticate them
if they're clicking on something how do
you verify access and so forth and all
of that's done at runtime the other side
of the dichotomy is in the
administration side if you go back to
the 5as that's I think number five and
in the administrative side that happens
out of band so typically a user will
sign up or you'll do a batch process and
move a bunch of user accounts and do
things like that so the administrative
side and the runtime side are decoupled
by and large and so you can use
orchestration in both worlds but you're
going to be doing it in different ways
so runtime identity orchestration is
going to handle the I would say the 5as
that happen as people are using things
and then on the governance or the
administrative side you're going to be
using the automation capabilities of
orchestration so for instance you may
have a situation where we're onboarding
a new user
and here's where these two things come
together so we have a a fictional bank
and the bank needs to verify information
about the user so that the person can't
create a fraudulent account and that may
involve checking a driver's license in
addition to some other
information and so you have this
multi-step process or a user journey to
sign up and get a new account and we
want to do this so that the user gets
access to the account and they become a
customer so we don't want them to do it
and then 3 days later have to come back
and say hey your account is ready we
need to do this in near real time or
just in time the jit approach so what
you could do is use orchestration to
combine that user experience they come
in they have a progressive profiling a
little bit of information tell us your
username tell us what company you're
part of tell us what state you live in
or country you live in and then as we
start to get that information that goes
into the orchestration decision tree and
so for instance based on that
information that we collected the first
step we may say ah you're a European
customer so therefore I'm going to have
you provide a valid European driver's
license or a whatever is appropriate
take a picture of that upload it and
then the orchestration software will
take that image and then send it to an
identity verification service as an
example wait to see if that checks out
and let's say that it does then the
orchestration system will get a response
back from the verification system saying
yes this is Eric and I you know I can
say that that worked so the third step
now is to issue a credential so that
this new customer never gets a password
in the first place so at that point we
may in step three enroll the user in a
multiactor passwordless credential so
for instance hey take a picture of this
QR code and then do something on your
phone and we'll link that all together
with this one transaction so at the end
of this three-step flow now the user has
an account they have been verified for
compliance purposes for know your
customer and they have a passwordless
authentication uh credential issued to
them all in a very seamless transparent
thing that should take maybe two or
three minutes and that is an example of
where we're doing Administration tasks
at runtime but being able to do them in
a very specific sequence an orchestrated
sequence that's an example of kind of
runtime me needs administrative so you
can do it all in a seamless way okay so
the automation aspects actually help in
taking care of the various identity
management systems and their own
specific needs because I guess the
systems connected to those specific
identity management systems need some
part of the attributes or the
information associated with the user but
not the rest so that's right and the
orchestration knows where to look for
all these beats due to the automation
implemented that's right and the way we
think about those identity services like
the authentication system and the
identity verification system and some
others so all of these are company's
identity services and they're all
fragmented they're provided by different
vendors they run in different places and
so part of what the abstraction layer is
doing is creating what we call an
identity fabric so all of your identity
systems they're aggregated behind a
common abstraction layer so that when it
comes time to authenticate this user
with this identity provider create an
account in this identity provider issue
a credential in this identity provider
the orchestration system is already
integrated with all of those identity
providers so they can do the crud
functions the change read update delete
on those identity providers through this
Orchestra layer so it's a really kind of
powerful notion to combine abstraction
layer with all of these infrastructure
components it's integrated with and
deliver it at runtime okay so now I was
thinking a couple of questions so one is
the automation here when we refer to
Automation in the context of identity
orchestration is is mainly about the
administration bits I would imagine also
some of the other Rays as well depending
on how you have to deal with the various
apis and things
but I guess for the administration Parts
is a big chunk of it yeah absolutely and
the typical use cases in user identity
are creating new users and deleting
users so onboarding and offboarding
those are very essential that's like the
main two scenarios and how you onboard a
user there's various steps and often you
have more than one system that needs to
be managed so
that kind of orchestrating multi-step
user Journeys is really part of both the
onboarding and the offboarding scenarios
yeah because I can imagine that is where
you really need a lot of automation if
you have disparate systems to somehow
synchronize to an extent with each other
but then I have now a question related
to security here now am I correct in
thinking that having this orchestration
layer that deals with different identity
systems might actually helping
segregating somehow information about
the users I mean I don't know if I'm
right or wrong so you correct me if I'm
wrong but I've got in my head that if we
had a single identity provider for all a
disparate set set of systems each of
them with its own specific needs and
requirements for the data they need this
seems to be a big kind of a central
point where pretty much everything about
the user is collected potentially a
security risk in a in a way or a privacy
risk as well but if we are orchestrating
different identity providers each of
them connected to some systems this
amount might actually help in
segregating bits of informations for the
user in a way that makes it less likely
to abuse privacy or security am I
correct in thinking this yeah absolutely
jaavan and I think here's a thing that a
lot of developers are surprised to find
out is that even if you're working with
a company that thinks of themsel as for
instance an American
company there are a lot of potential
European customers that come into this
application and an American company is
subject to the European privacy
directive right and so now all of a
sudden people in America think well why
do I care about European privacy
directive like we're run this in United
States I'm a American company well it's
because of the notion of crossborder
access and so when you think about this
it can be very expensive from A Fine
standpoint I think the EU privacy I just
read this week about a social media
company that had gotten a 370 million
fine because they didn't keep the
European data in Europe and instead it
went to America and then to China
reportedly so what do you do in that
situation well what you could do with
orchestration is say look we have users
that are are European users we're going
to hold them in a identity provider
that's entirely based in Europe and not
in America and then American identities
will be stored in the US we'll keep it
simple just those two places so now that
could be two different vendors could be
the same vendor but now you've got two
identity providers that you want to
access the same application but maintain
respect for the geography where those
user and the data privacy rules Supply
and so orchestration would allow you to
link those two at runtime and not make
you move and replicate data of European
users into America and vice versa so you
keep it it partitioned that's going to
save you a lot in overhead because of
these European privacy directives gdpr
there's a whole lot of reasons why that
can become a problem very quickly but
orchestration allows you to choose what
you want and use what you have wherever
it runs and so you can kind of have your
cake and eat it at the same time and I
guess this is possible because there is
no need for the orchestration system to
actually say that I have some for the my
orchestration deployed in the cloud
somewhere in Europe but to read data
from the US is well the orchestration
can simply ask questions about the user
things receive back response there is no
need to use data in transit and so kind
of read the data from the US and bring
it to Europe yeah the where the cables
and potentially causing all sorts of
privacy issues or maybe legal issues
exactly and and I think the main thing
is that orchestration layer does not
persist it is not an identity provider
itself it's like in virtualization
there's the
hypervisor and that runs on something
else it's not the server it looks like
the server but it's not the server right
it's a facade of the server itself and
what we do with orchestration is similar
in that we're not persisting the user
record from Europe in the America
because that's what the storage of data
is a lot of the problem right if you're
replicating user data or someone says
hey I don't want to have all of my
citizens data in a potentially foreign
world so that's where we number One
never persist that data and then the
other part is that you can ensure
encryption in motion and through the
transaction all the way through so that
when that user
is coming we can tokenize that user's
data we don't have to use the data
itself and so a lot of ways to keep that
information from moving from one
geography to the other and orchestration
is right in the middle making all of
that happen it's the connective tissue
designed to do that very thing and we've
got a lot of our customers are
multinational and they run into this all
the time and it's really interesting how
some of them have even use the same
vendor but have multiple instances where
they've got the European instance of
OCTA and the American instance of OCTA
they can't have the identities even
though it's the same identity system
they have to be in different places and
they use orchestration to say sure you
will be able to link these deliver that
user into an application but not violate
the data sovereignity that is needed in
that example okay and now a question
about another a the auditing so when you
put in orchestration system in place
what happens to the abil the auditing
abilities because we had several
identity providers maybe each of those
providing their own auditing mechanisms
what happens when you put orchestration
in place auditing gets a whole lot
better so the first thing is is
non-destructive meaning all the auditing
of the change logs and things like that
that that exist before you deploy
orchestration those don't go away right
all of those things continue to run the
way that they always have now when you
bring in orchestration you've got
another layer where you can add more
context and this layer is going to show
you the activity across identity
providers so it also means that you can
see application access across different
clouds so why is that important an it's
because you've got more of a single pane
of glass now that you can look at all of
these different systems and see how the
information of the transaction could
start on one cloud and end up on the
other and you can have continuity of
which user account was used even though
I went to multiple identity systems in
multiple clouds so auditing gets a whole
lot better I think there's a really
interesting opportunity
for having a single view of all of your
user access across your clouds and
between your cloud and on premises
environments and that's what you get
with orchestration because it creates a
whole new strata of layer rather of how
you can manage all of these different
systems put it all into one place and
that breaks a lot of the problems of
fragmentation that have been an issue
where where hey I see what's happening
in this Cloud I see what's happening
with this system but I can't see the
forest because of all these trees what
orchestration allows you to see is both
the forest and the trees because it is
managing all of it when we put identity
orchestration in place aren't we
creating a bit more complexity in the
system I mean we are putting more
services on top of what was already
there I think there's a good parallel
between virtualization and orchestration
so it's true right you're adding
software and so now we got a new thing
orchestration that we need to manage but
what it is itself is a management system
and so similar to the concerns that
people had with virtualization saying
well you know we have all of these
servers that we need to manage and if we
put them onto a hypervisor we still have
to manage those servers and the
hypervisor but what we found was that
that the hypervisor is the place to do
all of the management and so you
actually have a buil-in way to make
things consistent and that's similar to
what we're doing with identity
orchestration is we don't replace the
identity providers we create a new way
to link them all together and by doing
that we make a consistent for instance
policy can be made consistent across
these different fragmented systems using
policy
orchestration and we helped build a
standard for that called
idq and that's a way to use software for
free by the way it's all open source you
can get the cloud native Computing
Foundation it's not a sales pitch it's
just like a developer tool for like hey
you want to build Cloud native apps
here's a way to make your policies and
all your clouds work consistent and you
couldn't do that without orchestration
what you would be doing otherwise is
managing it in five different places and
with orchestration you can manage it
once and the orchestration then
propagates that change wherever it needs
to go through so you can reduce your
management significantly by putting in a
new piece of management software the
abstraction layer okay let's move to
implementation yeah just to have an idea
of the work involved let's put things
this way so first of all what are the
typical components of an identity
orchestration solution so we have talk
in in the abstract identity
orchestration but in practice what is it
when we have to deploy something what we
get to deploy or or to integrate so our
approach to it I could share that I
think there's there's other approaches
that people have taken but the one that
we found after building these kind of
systems for you know exis scale Cloud
platforms like we did at Oracle to the
biggest Enterprises and various
companies was to decouple the control
plane and the management plane and and
when I say that is the control plane is
where you set your rules and your
policies and so these are the things
that define how you authenticate Define
what access control and so forth and
then on the runtime side of the
inforcement identity plane depending on
what terminology you want to use we
think of it as the identity enforcement
plane that's what happens at runtime so
the management structure in our approach
is to use the cloud to configure your
rules and then use a piece of new kind
of software called an orchestrator that
runs in various distributed places close
to your applications and this
orchestrator is a
multi-functional thing it will act as a
proxy but it does more than proxy it can
act as a translation layer for uh
translating
different protocols into other protocols
for instance changing a samle protocol
into an open ID connect protocol right
so it's a translation server if you will
it can act as a service provider like
open ID or a SLE SP so it's this
multi-functional piece of software but
the simplest way to think of it as like
a proxy right and you can put this in
proximity to your application
so that any traffic going into the
application has to go through the
orchestrator once that traffic comes
through the orchestrator it looks at the
policy that it was given from the cloud
the control plane and so it can read it
without having to call home that's the
key thing distributed architectures you
don't want them all calling home because
you lose the benefit of spreading things
around and in this way with a control
plane you can also change some the way
the orators work without having to shut
down the system restart anything
basically so it's is a dynamic thing so
you can change policies or whatever you
need to change without too much effort
that's right you change your policy and
you publish that policy and through the
distributed architecture that policy
Finds Its way to all of the
orchestrators that use that and there's
an air gap between the orchestrator and
the control plane that's important
because if you're having to call home
for every decision that's not a
distributed system that's a centralized
system and you wouldn't be able to call
home on a cruise ship so the
orchestrator is a piece of software that
is actually installed on the customer
side say be it in the cloud or on
premises yeah the orchestrators are
distributed in our world the software
that we've built they're very high
performance and they're very small so
you can run them on a cell phone the
whole distribution is not even 50
megabytes so it's really intended to be
very high performance you run them in a
series if you use kubernetes so you
never have a single point of failure and
you can push them into these new form
factors I won't say this for sure but
don't be surprised if you see
orchestrators in automobiles because
cars are become even smarter and another
situation where you don't want to have
to call home to a network to see if
you're going to allow someone to have a
local service to a music service or
something like that so if you have the
right architecture you can push a very
small enforcement component out to all
these millions of cars to the 5G Network
Towers to mobile phones even so it's all
intended to solve identity in these
highly distributed multicloud worlds and
you got to do it very secure and you
have to make make sure that the
performance and latency don't become
issues and that's why we took the air
gap approach in our case how long does
it take typically for a company to
implement an identity orchestration
solution our record is less than 10
minutes to use our cloud service to get
up and running and to protect a real
live application so we can do that using
one identity provider and one
application start from zero and you can
up and running in in 10 minutes that's
our record when you look at a big
Enterprise their mindset is well we want
to think how do we do this for five
identity providers and 200 applications
and so in that world we call our
approach anyways is called live in five
which means five days and then your
production ready so typically in the
beginning you're going to say hey let's
plan our deployment what identity
systems are we going to integrate with
and what applications are we going to
secure the integration is plug-and
playay it's all visual it's all you
choose basically out of the fabric
options what you use and so that's like
a click operation and then on the
applications what you need to do is
provide basically four Fields what is
the URL when people log in what is the
URL when they log out what's an error
page and are there any areas in the web
application you want to treat
differently from a policy standpoint
like a dashboard versus login so it's
pretty quick now a last question about
emerging Trends or Technologies you know
in the field of identity orchestration
what is happening are there emerging
Trends directions things exciting things
that are happening or going to happen at
some point yeah there's a lot of really
interesting things that are happening I
think the biggest is that people are
under understanding that identity
orchestration is possible when we first
started this company in 2019 people said
there's no way you could do that that's
not possible and we'd have to just let
them use the software and say well
you're and all these other customers are
doing it so it exists it works but that
was a lot of convincing that we had to
do in every individual case now I think
what's happened is that we've been able
to make the software all self service so
people can just try it on their own so
that nice ability to give developers
their own control over things instead of
having to talk to a company they can go
do it themselves we think that's really
interesting the whole selfservice notion
and then I think the broader thing that
I'm excited about over the next couple
years is using the capability of the
orchestration data all of that audit
data we were talking about earlier to
aggregate that all in a common data Lake
and what would you want to do with that
you'd want to train it to do some Ai and
I know everyone talked about AI we've
been very pragmatic in how we're
thinking about it because for us it's a
way to take our automation to the next
level we want to train it on what we do
that no one else does and that's deal
with this data that comes out of these
Fabrics that we create and so I think in
the not too distant future you'll be
able to have an AI powered co-pilot to
watch what's happening across your
orchestration world all of these
different clouds all of these different
applications see when something weird is
happening and do something about it
automatically using orchestration so
we're kind of merging or converging the
sensor and the enforcement and the
integration all in one platform and I
think that's going to be the future
because the reality is giovan you know
this the bad guys are using Ai and
they're trying to get in and so we are
looking at how they're using it and most
of what we're seeing right now is
they're using it to write better fishing
emails so we really are trying to
encourage our customers get rid of
passwords if there's anything I could
leave your audience with is come up with
a password elimination plan as soon as
you can because if you don't these Bad
actors are they're using all of these
hey chat GPT write a really convincing
fishing email I think they probably
won't write it in that exact words but
you get the idea right and all of a
sudden we've got all sorts of new
attacks that are coming in we got to get
ahead of it so being able to to do
something about it detect it and
mitigate it that's really where I'm
excited with
orchestration okay thank you Eric I
think think we did a quite a good job in
introducing identity orchestration I
certainly learned a lot during this
interview how can people can get in
touch with you to find out more well we
have our websites the probably the best
place to go strata doio spelled s r a t
a. we'll put that in the interview links
yeah that'd be great and then the other
place would be the cloud native
Computing foundation for the standards
around identity ql I think that's the
other place I would I point your
audience to CN cf. org look for idq
we'll add all those links to the
interview page wonderful thank you for
coming to the interview Eric it's been a
real pleasure and this is javanon for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at Team
e-r. net this and all other episodes of
SE radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]